Finding Aid for Council About Parochiaid Records 1970-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Council About Parochiaid records 1970-1978
Council About Parochiaid
1 linear ft.
Michigan organization formed to oppose public aid to non-public schools and students, variously known as CAP, and the Council Against Parochiaid. Minutes of meetings, correspondence, and other materials relating to their support of Proposal C in the Michigan election of 1970, and their opposition to Proposal H (the Voucher Plan) in the election of 1978.
85511 Bh 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were received in 1970 and 1979 from the organization and through its executive director Mrs. Kathryn A. Boucher (donor nos. 4981 and 6282 ).
The record group is open for research.
The Council About Parochiaid (also known as the Council of Organizations and Others for Education About Parochiaid, and the Council Against Parochiaid) is a non-profit coalition of organizations and individuals formed in 1970 with principal offices in Lansing. The Council About Parochiaid or CAP's primary activity has been to oppose the flow of public funds to private and parochial schools. As of 1978, membership in CAP included some thirty organizations and individuals. Among the former category are: the American Civil Liberties Union, the Anti-Defamation League, Americans United for Separation of Church and State, The League of Women Voters of Michigan, Michigan Alliance of Black Educators, Michigan Association of School Boards, Michigan Education Association, Michigan Federation of Teachers, and the United Methodist Church.
After the Michigan State Legislature adopted a measure permitting the flow of public funds to non-public schools in 1969, CAP planned and coordinated a statewide initiative petition and political campaign seeking passage of a constitutional amendment to prohibit public aid to non-public schools and students. The proposed amendment appeared on the 1970 ballot as Proposal C. In that year Michigan voters rejected public tax support for church-related and other non-public schools through the passage of Proposal C.
Though continuing to hold meetings, CAP remained relatively dormant until 1978 when the Citizens for More Sensible Financing of Education (CSF) organized an initiative petition placing a voucher plan, Proposal H, on the ballot. Because this measure would shift local property taxes for the operation of schools and other educational purposes to the state personal income tax and/or single business tax, and require the distribution of educational vouchers to support the attendance of each pupil at the public or non-public school of the parent's or guardian's choice, CAP viewed Proposal H as a pro-parochiaid measure. CAP-78, the political action arm and state ballot committee to oppose the voucher plan amendment unsuccessfully sought the disqualification of the petitions through the State Supreme Court, and then organized a successful campaign to defeat Proposal H on the ballot.
These papers from the files of Kathryn Boucher, Executive Director of CAP, contain organizational and campaign materials in addition to newspaper clippings covering the two major state ballot proposals of the 1970's concerning public aid to non-public schools and students in the state of Michigan. The collection includes lists, bulletins, news releases, financial statements, mailings, workshop materials, papers from local coalitions, poll results and legal materials in addition to papers from the organization, United We Can, and a file containing "pro-parochiaid" materials. Also in the collection are notices and minutes of meetings for the years 1970-1972 and 1977-1978, and correspondence, 1970-1973, and 1977-1978. The 1970 correspondence record a variety of personal positions of Michigan Education Association members on the issue of parochiaid.
Subjects:
Church schools--Michigan--Finance.; Education--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1970.; Elections--Michigan--1978.; Parochiaid.; Council About Parochiaid.; Government aid to private schools--Michigan.
- Meetings
  (minutes, notices, and related material)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
    (folder 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
    (folder 2)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
    (folder 3)
  - 1977 (Box 1)
    (folder 4)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
    (folder 5)
- Correspondence
  - 1970 (Box 1)
    (folder 6)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
    (folder 7)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
    (folder 8)
  - 1977 (Box 1)
    (folder 9)
  - January-June 1978 (Box 1)
    (folder 10)
  - July-December 1978 (Box 1)
    (folder 11)
- Proposal "C" (Anti-parochiaid) Yes Campaign, 1970
  - Lists (Box 1)
    (organizations, contact people, distribution centers, coordinators)
    (folder 12)
  - Bulletins (Box 1)
    (folder 13)
  - News Releases (Box 1)
    (folder 14)
  - Campaign material; include blank initiative petition, handouts, flyers, fact sheets, time table, and related material (Box 1)
    (folder 15)
  - Legal material (Box 1)
    (folder 16)
  - Printed materials (news clippings and reprints) (Box 1)
    (folder 17)
- Proposal "H" (Voucher Plan) No Campaign, 1978
  - Lists (Box 1)
    (organizations, speakers bureau, committees, distribution centers)
    (folder 18)
  - Charts: Organization and Campaign Designs, and Information Tasks-Timeline (Box 1)
    (folder 19)
  - News Releases (Box 1)
    (folder 20)
  - Financial Statements (Box 1)
    (folder 21)
  - Mailings (newsletters and related materials) (Box 1)
    (folder 22)
  - CAP-78 Local Coalitions (Box 1)
    (folder 23)
  - CAP Regional Workshops, May 12, 1978 (Box 1)
    (schedules, resource teams, lists)
    (folder 24)
  - Campaign material; include handouts, flyers, pamphlets, radio spots, newspaper ads, bumper sticker, and Michigan Association of School Board's position papers (Box 1)
    (folder 25)
  - Poll results (Box 1)
    (folder 26)
  - Legal material (complaint for mandamus) (Box 1)
    (folder 27)
  - Legal material (Box 1)
    (Board of State Canvassers meeting and sampling plans and decisions criteria for petition validation)
    (folder 28)
  - Legal Developments Affecting Education (Box 1)
    (folder 29)
  - United We Can material; including platform, mailings, handouts, newsletter and related material (Box 1)
    (folder 30)
  - Pro-parochiaid material; including newsclippings, blank Initiative Petition, CSF Board of Directors list, CSF Newsletters, press release reprints, and booklet (Box 1)
    (folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Voucher Plans (other states) (Box 1)
    (folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters (Box 1)
    (folder 34)
- Printed material
  - Church and State, 1978 (Box 1)
    (folder 35)
  - Reprints (Box 1)
    (folder 36)
  - News clippings, 5 folders (Box 1)
    (folders 37-42)
  - UPI Releases (Box 1)
    (folder 43)